<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Welcome to WS Policy</title>
	</properties>
	
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1" />
		<meta content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1" />
		<meta name="generator" content="amaya 9.2.1, see http://www.w3.org/Amaya/" />
	</head>
	
	<body>
	
	<section>

	<h1>Welcome to Apache WS-Commons Policy</h1>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>Web Services (WS)-Commons Policy provides an implementation of WS-Policy 
specification.It provides a convenient model to process any policy information 
at runtime. In other words, it allows you to convert any policy to an object 
(which is its runtime representation) and play with it as you like. You could 
normalize it and then print it if you want to convert your original policy into
a standard format. Else you could merge or intersect that policy object with
another policy object and print it to see how the merge / or intersect looks
like.</p>

<p><strong>WS-Policy specification</strong> define <a
href="#operations">policy operations</a> to manipulate policies.
WS-Commons/Policy framework support all these operations which are extremely
useful when trying to do complex policy manipulations</p>

<h3>What is WS-Policy?</h3>

<p>A <strong>WS-policy</strong> is a set of requirements that have to be met
in order to consume a web service.</p>

<p>A requirement can be domain specific. For instance, if your policy demands
that you need security token type, then its a primitive requirement.
<strong>PrimtiveAssertion</strong> class represents such requirements in
<strong>Commons/Policy framework</strong>.</p>

<p>Another requirement would be to meet several assertions in a certain way.
For instance, an assertion would require all its child assertions be met
while another assertion may require exactly one of its child assertions be
met. Such assertions are known as <strong>CompositeAssertions</strong>. If
assertion implements CompositeAssertion marker-interface, it's an indication
that this assertion is of CompositeAssertion type. For instance
AndCompositeAssertion, XorCompositeAssertion and Policy are of
CompositeAssertion type.</p>

<p>If you consider the <strong>AndCompositeAssertion</strong> it requires all
its child terms be met. If its <strong>XorCompositeAssertion</strong> type,
it requires that exactly one of its child terms be met. Both Policy and
AndCompositeAssertion requires same behavior except that in
<strong>Policy</strong>, policy object is the outer most element.</p>
<a name="operations"></a>
<h3>Policy Operations</h3>

<p>The object model in WS-Commons/Policy becomes very handy when it comes to
<strong>policy operation</strong>s. For instance you could invoke normalize()
method on a policy object which will return a new policy object which has the
same implication, but in a standard format.</p>

<p>If you merge a policy object with another policy object it will return a
new policy object which represents the merged policies of those two objects.
If you could satisfy any policy alternative available in the resultant
object, it is guaranteed that at least one policy alternative of both policy
objects could be met.</p>

<p>One interesting application of policies would be to identify which policy
alternatives that both parties can agree upon. The simple solution is to
intersect the two policy objects and get the resultant policy object. It
would contain all possible policy alternatives that both parties agree
upon.</p>

<p>Commons/Policy framework is now reaching its maturity. It is used in other
web services projects like Axis2, Sandehsa2 and WSS4J to process any policy
information they require. Recently it passed all the WS Policy Interop Round1
which is aimed to test the correctness of object model. And it seems safe to
say that bright future is ahead.</p>

<p>You can learn how to use Apache WS-Policy by checking out our <a href="userguide.html" target="_blank">User's Guide</a>
</p>

<h2>Background and Motivation</h2>
<p>Web services is an emerging technology with enormous promise. The biggest advantage of web services is its cross platform capability. In other words, Web services allow applications to communicate in a platform independent manner. However, communication between non trivial Web services is not that straight forward. For instance, if WS-Security is enabled, the client must determine if WS-Security is optional or madatory for this service. If it is mandatory then client must determine the security token type the server understands or it prefers. After which client must determine whether to sign the messages and which parts to sign. Finally client must determine whether to encrypt the message and if so what algorithm to use. Without such information, integrating two Web services would be a next to impractical.</p> 

<p>So far there was no standard way to convey this information except documentation or emails from developer to developer. WS-Policy addresses this issue and provides a standard framework to express these additional details. However, it is left to the authors of other specifications to extend this framework to convey any specific details that fall within the scope of those specifications.</p>

<h2>Latest Release</h2>
<h3>5th March 2006 -Apache WS-Commons Policy version 0.90 Released!</h3>
<h4>Key Features in this Release</h4>
<ol>
  <li>Fully compliant with latest WS-Policy Specification</li>
  <li>Passes WS-Policy Interop ROUND1 Test Suite</li>
</ol>

<h2>Resources</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a
    href="https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/webservices/commons/modules/policy/" target="_blank">ws-commons policy</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2004/09/policy/ws-policy.pdf" target="_blank">Web
    Services Policy Framework (WS-Policy)</a></li>
  <li>Samaranayake, Sanka. January 2006. <a
    href="http://www.wso2.net/2006/01/web_services_policy_why_what_how" target="_blank">Web
    services Policy - Why, What &amp; How.</a></li>
</ul>
	</section>
	
	</body>
</document>
